A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Belem, Brazil, RG 6, SG 2 FA416
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, field offices, Belem, Brazil, RG 6, SG 2
1954-1970
1960-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation. Belem (Brazil)
Rockefeller Foundation
FA416
3.13 Cubic Feet 1 legal document box, 7 letter document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 20 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
The Rockefeller Foundation operated several field laboratories in the 1950s and 1960s, in conjunction with its virus research program centered at the Rockefeller Institute in New York.
The field office in Belem, Brazil, operated from 1954–1971 as a laboratory for the study of arthropod- or insect-borne viruses. Created in collaboration with the Servico Especiales de Saude Publica (Special Service of Public Health), the Belem virus laboratory sought to classify these viruses and examine the way they presented in humans and domesticated animals.
Ottis R. Causey was the first director of the virus laboratory. He and his wife, Calista Eliot Causey, established the laboratory in 1954, and Causey remained director until 1963. Causey received his Doctor of Science degree in entomology, parasitology, and bacteriology from Johns Hopkins University. During his career with the Rockefeller Foundation, Causey devoted himself to the field of arbovirology. Under his tenure, the lab isolated about 1,600 viruses, of which 50 were found to be distinct viruses.
In the mid-1960s, the Rockefeller Foundation began to phase out its virus research program. The New York laboratory was incorporated into the Yale School of Medicine in 1964, becoming the Yale Arbovirus Research Unit, and several of the foundation's field laboratories integrated with universities or government research agencies. Robert E. Shope, M.D., directed the Belem laboratory from 1963 through June 1965, and was succeeded by John P. Woodall, who served until the field office's closing in 1971.
In the course of its existence, the Belem Virus Laboratory was responsible for isolating many viruses. Seeking to determine which viruses were present in their specific region, researchers studied blood samples from monkeys, mice, and humans. This isolation of viruses gave information about the prevalence of certain viruses and the conditions under which they were likely to occur. The laboratory established different methods for rapidly classifying viruses and new ways for monitoring the effects of the viruses on humans and animals. The laboratory made significant contributions to the knowledge of virus activity and lifecycles.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices include:
FA395 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Paris. FA396 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, New Dehli, India. FA397 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Cali, Colombia. FA398 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Offices, Mexico. FA399 Rockefeller Foundation records, Field Office, Ankara, Turkey.
File Plan
RG 6.2.
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Belem Field Office records arrived at RAC during the initial transfer of Rockefeller Foundation records to Hillcrest, August 8-18, 1975.
The material was not officially accessioned at the time of tranfer, and was retroactively accessioned by RAC as 2012:086.
Scope and Contents
The Belem Field Office records document the activities of the Belem Virus Laboratory from 1954 to 1970. Records consist of administrative and professional correspondence relating to laboratory operations, research activities, and communications and cooperation with researchers at other virus labs and research organizations, particularly in Latin America, Trinidad, and the U.S.
Virus diseases; Virology; Virologists; Viruses -- Research; Viruses; Virus -- Classification
- Belem Virus Laboratory, 1954-1970; 1960-1970; 1; 3.52 Cubic Feet 8 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Series 1 is arranged alphabetically, and primarily further arranged chronologically.
  - Africa
    - 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brazil except FSEP
    - 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Field Parties, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - South America
    - 1956-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Anthropod Borne Virus Information Exchange
    - 1954-1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1964 January-February (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1964 March-July (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1964 August-December (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1965 January-March (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1965 April-December (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ottis R. Causey
    - 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Cayenne, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Contracts, Agreements and Authorizations (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Wilbur G. Downs
    - 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Grants and Fellowships
    - 1959-1964 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - National Institute of Health: Arbovirus Reagents
    - 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - 1964 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - 1964 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Other Countries
    - 1956 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Pan American Sanitary Bureau
    - 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1961-1970 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Panama - Colombia - MARU - Bethesda
    Scope and Contents
    MARU refers to the Middle America Research Unit, which was a facility established in the Canal Zone by the National Institutes of Health. The file contains correspondence with researchers in these organizations and countries.
    - 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - 1962 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - 1963 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Personnel (Box 5, Folder 43)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from scholarly access; contains personnel records
  - Rio
    - 1954-1959 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Rockefeller Foundation: New York
    - 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - 1964-1970 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Rockefeller Foundation: Virus Labs
    - 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - 1960 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - 1961 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Telegrams
    - 1955-1958 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - 1959-1962 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Trinidad
    - 1954-1959 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - 1960 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - 1961 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - 1962 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - USA except Rockefeller Foundation
    - 1950-1959 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - 1962 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - 1963 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - 1964 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Visitors
    - 1959-1966 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Yale Arbovirus Research Unit
    - 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 78)